Dear Ms. Hoan Hi, I am currently practicing the Ksitigarbha Sutra
xin cô Hoan Hỉ con đang tu tập bài số tá
to resolve my husband's illness. My husband, born in 1982,
để hóa giải bệnh chồng con sinh năm 1982
suffers from emotional disorders, including depression, mania,
bị bệnh rối loạn cảm xúc trầm cảm hưng
psychosis, and paranoia. He was
phấn loạn thần thần kinh hoang tưởng đã
hospitalized at Bach Mai Hospital's psychiatric department for a period,
có một thời gian vào bệnh viện Bạch Mai
but his condition
điều trị khoa tâm thần nhưng bệnh không
worsened and didn't improve. My family requested to
giảm mà nặng hơn và gia đình con đã xin
take him home. I chant the Ksitigarbha Sutra at home, and his
về con có tụng kinh địa tạng ở nhà hiện
condition has improved. However, he is hindering
tại nhà con bệnh cải thiện nhưng cản trở
my practice, preventing me from listening to Dharma teachings and
con tu tập không cho con nghe pháp và
from practicing at home. That is, when
không cho về tu tập Tức là cái lúc mà
the illness subsides, it doesn't hinder me, but when it lessens
bệnh lặng thì chưa cản trở đến lúc giảm
a little, it becomes a hindrance, right? When it lessens
đi một tí thì cản trở phải không ạ giảm
a little, he becomes lucid, right? If it doesn't
đi một tí thì nó tỉnh phải không em Đấy
lessen a little, it becomes a hindrance. Otherwise, if it's just a
giảm đi một tí thì cản trở Còn nếu không
mental illness, he won't
thì cứ cho vào bệnh thần kinh thì chả
know anything and will be hindered. Then, when I start practicing and dedicate
biết gì mà cản trở đến lúc tu tập cho
some merit, he becomes lucid, and only then will he listen.
một ít hồi hướng Phước nó tỉnh lên rồi
One person
thì tỉnh lên rồi thì mới nghe Người này
listens, another encourages him, and that's when the
nghe người kia xui rồi nó mới sinh ra
hindrance arises, right? That's not it. That's how it happens
cản trở phải không em Đấy chưa Cái đấy
a lot. Now, if they
thì gặp rất nhiều thế thôi bây giờ thì
hinder me from practicing like that,
cản trở không cho Tu được như thế thì
I have no choice but to practice in secret. Yen,
thì mình đành phải tu kín thôi chứ sao
please read more. I
được nhá Yến đ xin đọc thêm ạ Ở nhà con
am practicing at home.  For 15 days, I followed
đang tu tập được 15 ngày theo chương
program number 8, but I had to practice when my
trình số 8 nhưng con phải tu tập khi nhà
family wasn't home. Once, when my family
con không có nhà và có một lần nhà con
came home while I was practicing, they threw the
đã về khi con đang tu tập nhà con đã vứt
Ksitigarbha Sutra and the practice book number
quyển kinh Địa Tạng và quyển tu tập số
8 down from the second floor to the first, and
tám xuống từ tầng hai xuống tầng một và
cursed at me a lot. Since then, they have
chửi con rất nhiều từ hôm đó nhà con
n't spoken to me, haven't eaten at home, and wo
không nói chuyện không ăn cơm ở nhà nữa
n't answer my questions. They've
hỏi cũng không nói không trả lời và bắt
forced me to choose between practicing
buộc con phải lựa chọn Một là tu tập hai
or my family. They said they'd let me go to the temple
là gia đình và có nói là hôm nào về chùa
with them to listen to the
cùng với con để nghe cô hoặc thầy Trạch
Dharma teachings, and that it would be on Saturday or Sunday. Whether I
pháp và đi vào thứ bảy hoặc chủ nhật đi
go to the temple or not is up to my family; they won't let me decide. I hope you can help me find a way for my family to connect with Buddhism and not hinder me from going to the temple and support my practice. Even with my
con về chùa và ủng hộ cho con tu tập
husband
được được thì giữa một cái việc mà Chồng
being sick and going from hospital
đang bị bệnh như thế đi hết bệnh viện nọ
to hospital, now that he's recovered, it's
đến bệnh viện kia bây giờ tỉnh được rồi
still better to have my practice interrupted than to
cản trở mình tu tập vẫn tốt hơn là cái
be in a state of mental illness and worry about it, right?
lúc mà là vị thần kinh mà phải lo đúng
That would be wonderful. It means that even though they're
không Thế là vui rồi tức là dù rằng bây
hindering me now, I'm still less
giờ cản mình nhưng vẫn là
suffering.
người đỡ khổ rồi phải
No, of course, people also
không Thế thì tất nhiên là người ta cũng
have karmic connections, which is why
có những cái duyên nghiệp cho nên nó mới
illnesses arise. So now,
sinh ra các cái bệnh thế thì bây giờ thì
I can tell my husband, "Okay, I
mình có thể nói với chồng là thôi em
don't have to go to the temple, but I'll practice meditation
không có về chùa cũng được nhưng tu tập
to keep things peaceful." Thanks to my practice, I've
cho nó mát mẻ Chính nhờ em tu tập thì
also had good fortune come to him. My practice doesn't
cũng có cái duyên Phước đến với anh tu
lose anything. It's not like that, dear fellow
có mất đi đâu Cái gì đâu phải không quý
practitioners, it doesn't lose anything. And
đạo hữu không mất đi đâu Cái gì thế và
I just take advantage of the times when my husband is
mình thôi cứ tranh thủ lúc nào chồng
n't home to practice. Now that it's like this, I
không có nhà thì tu bây giờ là như thế
have to accept it, because if I want
rồi thì phải chịu chứ vì muốn cầu hạnh
happiness for myself, I have to try, right?
phúc cho mình thì phải phải cố gắng thôi
Actually, I don't have
phải không Chứ còn thực ra là mình có
any choice. When he's
lựa chọn nào đâu đâu ông ấy lúc ông thần
mentally ill, he doesn't know he's mentally ill.
kinh Ông có biết ông bị thần kinh đâu
Only I know he's mentally ill, and I suffer, but
chỉ có mình biết ông bị thần kinh mình
he doesn't suffer because he doesn't know he's suffering, right? A
khổ chứ ông có khổ đâu vì ông có biết
mentally ill person
đâu mà khổ phải không Cái người thần
doesn't know anything anymore, so you tell
kinh người ta chả biết gì nữa mà bảo
them they're suffering, even if they do, they do
người ta khổ người ta có khổ người ta
n't know they're suffering. But I'm the
cũng không biết người ta khổ nhưng mình
one serving the mentally ill person, so I'm the one who
là cái người phục vụ cái người thần kinh
suffers. That's why I'm afraid of suffering, so
mình mới khổ cho nên mình sợ khổ thì
I have to practice. If he's not
mình phải tu thế thôi còn ông ấy không
afraid of suffering, then I'll tell him, "You're
sợ khổ thế thì bảo anh là anh bị thần
mentally ill, you don't know what suffering is."  Because you're
kinh Anh không biết đâu là khổ vì anh
mentally ill, I'm the one who's suffering.
thần kinh rồi em mới là người thấy khổ
So, what should I do to
thôi Thế thì thôi thì em phải làm sao
lessen my suffering? To lessen my suffering, I just practice.
cho em bớt khổ thế em bớt khổ thì em cứ
That's my practice. I practice because I
tu việc đó là việc tu em chính vì lựa
chose family,
chọn gia đình cho nên em mới tu chứ
not because I chose between family and practice. It's simply that I chose
không phải giữa hai việc là một là lựa
family, so
gì đây là chẳng qua em chọn gia đình thì
I practice, right, dear fellow practitioners? It's not like I'd choose not to, but to practice on my own.
em tu thôi đúng không quý đạo hữu chứ có
If it weren't for my family, why would I practice? Right,
tu đâu Nếu không vì cái gia đình của
dear fellow
mình ý thì mình Tu làm gì phải không quý
practitioners? If I were alone, I wouldn't
đạo hữu Nếu là có một mình mình thì đâu
suffer, right, dear fellow practitioners? Living
có khổ phải không quý đạo hữu sống một
alone only brings suffering in
mình nó chỉ khổ về bệnh tật Thôi các quý
many aspects. Suffering
đạo hữu ạ Còn chưa khổ về phải nhiều mặt
because of my husband, suffering because of my wife, suffering because of my children, suffering
Khổ Vì Chồng khổ vì vợ khổ vì con khổ về
economically, suffering in many ways. That's why I practice to
kinh tế khổ về nhiều mặt cho nên mình tu
lessen the suffering.
cho nó bớt khổ
Because Buddhism is a religion of practice. I practice to
thôi Tại vì đạo Phật là đạo tu gì Tu để
escape suffering, not because I'm too happy. Only when I'm
thoát khổ chứ có phải là sướng quá mà tu
too miserable do I practice, dear fellow practitioners, right? Because I'm
đâu chỉ có khổ quá mới tu thôi các quý đ
too miserable, that's why I
hu phải không khổ khổ quá cho nên mới tu
practice all kinds of things.  If our family is
tập tất cả các việc gì mà gia đình mình
not at peace, it's all suffering, isn't it,
không được an lành đều là khổ phải không
dear fellow practitioners? Therefore, we need to
các quý đạo hữu ch nên chúng ta cần phải
practice to transform our karma so that
tu để chuyển hóa nghiệp để gia đình
our family can be at peace. That's all,
chúng ta được an lành Chỉ mỗi thế thôi
dear fellow practitioners.
mà các quý đạo hữu ạ
[music]
[âm nhạc]
I
nhá I